Guide to the Watermargin records, 1947-2012.
Watermargin records, 1947-2012.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Watermargin records, 1947-2012
37-4-446
Watermargin (Cornell University)
5.8 cubic ft.
Correspondence, Manuscripts, Photographs, Legal Documents, Printed Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, clippings, newsletters, photographs, minutes of meetings, programs, incorporation papers pertaining to a Cornell University cooperative living unit, with particular reference to social issues and visits from Eleanor Roosevelt, Marion Anderson and Norman Thomas.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Co-op founded as a non-discriminatory fraternity.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, clippings, newsletters, photographs, minutes of meetings, programs, incorporation papers pertaining to a Cornell University cooperative living unit, with particular reference to social issues and visits from Eleanor Roosevelt, Marian Anderson and Norman Thomas.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Watermargin (Cornell University); Anderson, Marian R., 1897-1993.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University--Societies, etc.
Subjects:
Cooperative societies--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Student cooperatives--New York (State)--Ithaca.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Watermargin Papers: Printed Material, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Watermargin Papers: Newsletters, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Watermargin Papers: In the Margin, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Watermargin Papers: Newspaper Clippings, 1948-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Watermargin Papers, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Brochure and newsletter "The Marginal", Spring 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Group Photos - 2004 and 2006; CD of photos from Iron Chef Competition (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Group Photos [transferred from box 7, folder 1], 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Papers, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 103 McGraw Place, 2009; DVD-2671 (Box 1)
  "Sixty years after Watermargin's founding, Wei (Cornell '02) tracked down the surviving founders and several first generation alumni in order to document their stories and accomplishments of the beloved house located on Ithaca's 103 McGraw Place."
- Watermargin - Origins - Incorporation, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Certificate of Incorporation (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Origins - Constitution, meaning of the name, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Eleanor Roosevelt's visit, memoranda, 1947-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Foundation/Fundraising, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Early House Operations, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Brochures (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Brochures (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Conference committee information, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Conference - publicity, information, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Conference - "Inter-Group Living and the College Campus", 1950 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Conference - personal correspondence (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Applications for those attending the Watermargin Conference and Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Conference material (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Conference - correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Conference - Sourcebook, Session Minutes, Publicity, February 18-20, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Conference Correspondence - from other universities, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- College Exchange Weekend Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Farm Weekend, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Education Committee Correspondence, 1940's-1960's (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Speaker Series, 1950's-1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Langston Hughes - Programs, signed book The Dream Keeper (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Scott Hamilton's correspondence, 1950's (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Field Trips - Arkansas and NYC and bound copy of "Watermargin Arkansas Study Trip", 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Education Committee Correspondence, 1951-1963, 1980's-1990's (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Social Activities, 1950's-1980's (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Intergroup Relations in Ithaca (Box 2, Folder 28)
- House Activities - Blood Bank, 1950's-1960's (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Publications Committee Reports, 1940's (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Special Projects Committee (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Committees - Nominating, Dedication, Communications, Secretarial, etc., 1950's (Box 2, Folder 32)
- "In the Margin" - publication, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- "In the Margin", 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- "In the Margin"; books of quotes and programs; "Watermelon, Inc", 1950's-1987 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Newspaper clippings, 1940's-1950's (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Photographs - Eleanor Roosevelt (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Photographs - group picture of the Founders and others (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Photographs - speakers (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photographs - unidentified (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Photographs - unidentified (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Photographs (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Negatives (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Photographs - Campus Scenes (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Songs and Certificates (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Watermargin Activities and posters, 1948-1990's (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Watermargin cookbook, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence - miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Annual Reports, 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Annual Reports, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Annual Reports, 1983-1993 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Cooperatives at Cornell (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Proposal that a National Association for Intercultural Living be formed (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Cooperatives elsewhere - N. American Student Cooperative League (NASCL) (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Education Committee (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Education Committee, 1950's (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Board of Directors, 1950's-1960's (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Foreign Students Fund - Alumni Association, 1960's (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Newsletter - Alumni, 1970-1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Newsletters - Alumni, 1948-1969 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Letters to Alumni (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Minutes - Watermargin Membership Meetings, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Minutes - Watermargin Membership Meetings, 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Minutes - Watermargin Membership Meetings, 1956-1960 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Minutes - Watermargin Membership Meetings, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Minutes - Watermargin Membership Meetings, 1969-1981 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Minutes - Watermargin Membership Meetings, 1982-1990's (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Watermargin - Executive Committee Minutes, 1950-1959 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Watermargin - Executive Committee Minutes, 1960-1970's (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Watermargin - Board of Directors Material, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Watermargin - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1949-1990's (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Watermargin - Education Committee Minutes (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Watermargin - Social Committee Minutes (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Correspondence, 1940's-1950's (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1950's (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1960's (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1970's (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1980's (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Correspondence - Co-op Crisis, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- 45th Reunion, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Membership Lists (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Membership Lists (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Membership Lists (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Membership Lists (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Articles about Alumni (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Special Housing - Annex, 1960's (Box 4, Folder 19)
- House Expenditures, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- House Maintenance Records, 1950's-1990's (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Policies - Insurance, 1970's-1980's (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Residential Life Material, 1970's-1990's (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Insurance Offered, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Slides - M. Anderson Concert, Farm and Work Party, others, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Photos of Members (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Cassette tapes: 45th Reunion Conference - ACTWV Hall-NYC (Dec. 1993) - Death Penalty in the 1990's - John Blume - Tom Levanduski - His experience in the Persian Gulf (April 1992) (Box 4)
- 16mm Film: Norman Thomas, Eleanor Roosevelt, One unidentified (Box 4)
- Reel to Reel Film - Education Committee - Speaker Series (Box 4)
- Tin Photo Block (Box 4)
- Watermargin due cards (Box 4)
- Not for Profit - Financial Information (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Watermargin - Education Programs (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Watermargin - Annual Reports/Bylaws, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Watermargin - flyers, clippings, programs of events, 1948-1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Watermargin - Insurance Information, 1979-1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- NASCO (North American Students of Cooperation) newsbriefs, pamphlets, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- NASCO - brochures, annual reports (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Budgets, 1948-1960's (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Financial Correspondence, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Watermargin - Financial Records, 1957-1963 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Watermargin - Financial Records, 1955-1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Financial Records, 1970's (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Financial Records, 1980's-1990's (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Watermargin - Balance Sheets, 1949-1954 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Watermargin - Balance Sheets, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Watermargin - Balance Sheets, 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- House Operations (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Appraisal Report, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Proposed By-laws and Amendments (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Proposed By-laws and Amendments (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Constitution and By-laws of Watermargin (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Constitution and By-laws of Watermargin (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Constitution and By-laws of Watermargin (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Watermargin - Minutes, By-laws, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Membership - forms, letters (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Membership - correspondence, 1948-1950's (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Membership Lists (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Membership Cards (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Membership Cards (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Membership Cards (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Miscellaneous correspondence and memoranda; Handmade poster, 1940's-1980's (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Dance Photos, 1950-1952 (Box 6)
- Dance Photos, 1954-1955 (Box 6)
- Dance Photos, 1958-1966 (Box 6)
- Group Photos, 1959-1962 (Box 6)
- Group Photos, 1965-1967, 1969 (Box 6)
- Group Photos, 1975, 1977-1979 (Box 6)
- Group Photos, 1981-1984 (Box 6)
- Group Photos, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
- Group Photos, 1991-1994 (Box 6)
- Group Photos, 1997-1999 (Box 6)
- Group Photos, 2001-2012 (Box 6)
- Phonograph Record: Bad Company Rough Diamonds (Box 6)
- Posters (Box 6)
- News Clippings (Box 6)
- Watermargin Photos [transferred to box 1, folder 8], 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous Papers [transferred to box 1, folder 8], 2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Friends of Watermargin, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Goals, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 11/21/2000 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Correspondence and Articles, 1999-2001 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Watermargin, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- News from, Watermargin, 1998-2001 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- 1999-2002 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Watermargin Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Watermargin: Photos, Correspondence, Directories, etc., 1999-2002 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- History: "What is Watermargin?", 1948-51; 1956,; 1962,; 1966,; 1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Taxes - Exemption, 1950, 1952, 1954; 1952,; 1954 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Jack Sheinkman/Labor files, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 13)